Hi everyone. This is Ravi. Welcome to my
YouTube channel.
As you all know, I've started publishing
a series of YouTube videos on AI-based
test automation concepts by using the
modern test automation tools available
in the market.
So, this is the playlist AI-based test
automation using agents, agentic AI, and
MCP servers. So, this playlist consists
of 25 plus YouTube videos covering from
intermediate level to the advanced level
concepts of AI-based test automation
using different modern tools available
in the market. Coming to Tricentis
Tosca, I've published 61
YouTube videos covering beginner's
level, intermediate level, and advanced
level concepts of Tricentis Tosca test
automation. So, this Tricentis Tosca is
a no-code platform. We have automated
end-to-end test cases by using this
no-code platform. And also, I've
published 35 YouTube videos
>> [snorts]
>> for real-time scenarios and how can we
solve the obstacles in the real time. I
would recommend you guys to visit these
two playlists to understand the
Tricentis Tosca test automation
concepts. I'm going to leave the link
for these two playlists in the
description.
Please do subscribe to the channel,
click on bell icon, you'll receive
notifications whenever I publish more
videos.
Don't forget to like and share the
video. Thank you.
So, this is our lesson one
on agentic AI concepts by using the
Tricentis Tosca.
So, as part of this lesson,
I'm going to introduce you to the
agentic AI concepts by using the
Tricentis Tosca. So, basically, we are
going to automate our end-to-end test
cases
with the help of agentic AI features in
Tricentis Tosca
by using the plain English language
prompting.
So, first of all, what is that agentic
AI that helps in automating the test
cases with plain English language
prompting?
So, this is the feature Tosca agentic
test automation is the inbuilt feature
that Tricentis has developed.
By using this
agent, you can start automating your
test cases with plain English language.
So, let me explain you how can we
install
and how can we register for the free
trial version of Tosca agentic test
automation?
So, first of all,
there is
a 14 days trial version.
14 days free trial version is available
to access the Tosca agentic test
automation features. So, this is the URL
that you need to follow. I'm going to
paste this URL in the description.
As soon as you open this URL, you can
see the right side, this is the screen
it will open.
Where you need to provide your business
email
and you need to provide first name, last
name,
country,
your phone number, and your job title,
and then you need to agree to the
marketing communications.
And then click on request trial. So,
this will trigger
an email to the business email address.
And then, you need to follow the
instructions specified in the email.
So, when you get instructions, once you
click on that particular email link,
that will take you to the Tricentis
Tosca cloud
application where you need to provide
your organization name. Once you provide
your organization name, you will be
receiving one unique URL.
http://yourorganizationname.my.tricentis.com.
So, this is your unique URL for your
Tricentis Tosca cloud access.
So, once you get a Tricentis Tosca cloud
access,
then
you can start exploring the agentic AI
capabilities by using Tosca agentic test
automation feature.
So, by end of this lesson, you will be
able to explain how agentic test
automation in Tricentis Tosca interprets
plain language instructions to create
end-to-end test cases
with plain English language
instructions.
And then, you will be able to describe
how Tosca autonomously generates the
modules as well
and it can verify the data and it can
execute the created test cases from the
plain English language prompting itself.
So, basically, with simple plain English
language prompting, you will be able to
create your
test cases, test steps,
test data validations, and also you'll
be able to create your modules where the
element locators will be stored. All
these can be achieved with simple plain
English language.
So, now let me show you what is the
difference between automating your test
cases by using Tricentis Tosca without
agentic AI capabilities
and automating the test cases using
Tricentis Tosca with agentic AI
capabilities. What is the difference?
Let me show you.
So, traditional automation method is
without AI agent.
Without agentic AI, right? So, that
means you are using a no-code platform,
but you are not using your agentic AI
capabilities. So, in this particular
approach, what we do, we generally
create the modules first
to capture the element locators.
And then, you will be saving all the
modules. Once you create the modules,
then you will start scanning all system
under test elements and the properties
required for automation. This is your
second step.
And then, what we need to do, we need to
create a test cases. And then, you need
to define and create test steps
mapping the above modules that we
created.
Right? And then, you need to define the
test step values for each test step in
the test cases.
And then, you need to run the test case,
debug for any issues. So, this is your
traditional method without agentic AI
capabilities. So, what about
agentic AI automation in Tricentis
Tosca? In agentic AI automation
approach, first what we are going to do,
we are going to simply prepare a natural
language prompting. That means you're
going to prepare natural language
prompting with manual test cases.
Basically, you're going to write the
manual test cases in natural language.
And then, by using this Tosca agentic
test automation, you can straight away
automate all your test cases. So, rest
of all the steps from step one
to step six will be taken care by your
agentic AI, your agent itself. You need
not to perform step one, two, three,
four, five, six manually.
There is no manual effort at all. You
need not to create modules, you need not
to scan all the modules or elements, you
need not to create test cases, you need
not to create test steps, you need not
to execute the test cases, also.
Everything will be taken care by your
agentic AI automation or everything will
be taken care by the new agent
introduced by Tricentis Tosca called
Tosca agentic test automation. So, now
without delay,
let us jump on to Tricentis Tosca
and start exploring the features of
agentic AI
or start exploring the features of Tosca
agentic test automation.
With simple natural language prompting,
you will be able to create the
end-to-end test automation. And you'll
be able to publish the test results as
well.
So, once you complete subscribing for
the trial version, and then once you
complete the registration process
from the email by using your
organization, you'll be receiving a URL.
What is the URL? Your organization So,
this will be your
Tricentis Tosca cloud URL. Okay? Once
you land onto your Tricentis Tosca cloud
URL for the first time, it gives you all
the
quick start guide. So, it gives you
quick start guide. Okay? I'm going to
explain you what is this quick start
guide. Before that, so when you click on
this Tosca agentic test automation, this
is the new feature that we are going to
talk about in this session. What is
that? Taska agentic test automation.
This is your agentic AI-based test
automation. Okay, so once you click on
this icon for the first time,
it will ask you to authenticate.
So, because I've already authenticated,
it is not asking me to authenticate.
In your case, it will ask you to enter
the organization name that you have used
while registering
for the trial version. So, you need to
enter your organization name. And then
click on continue. Then, that
organization name will be validated in
the back end. If the organization name
is valid, then it will ask you to enter
your username and password that you
created while registering with the trial
version. Okay? So, you need to provide
your username and password. Then, you
will see this screen from where you can
start
automating your test cases from the
natural language. So, now
let us see a traditional method
how we used to automate our test cases
before we talk about agentic AI test
automation. So, let me quickly walk you
through the steps that are involved if I
want to automate my test cases by using
the traditional method without using the
agentic AI concepts. So, let's go to
build, go to all assets.
So, here
first what we need to do, we need to
capture the elements that are required
to automate your application.
So, this is our application
which is
vehicle insurance application, which is
a demo application provided by Tricentis
Tosca. So, this is used to get a
quotation for your vehicle insurance.
So, let's automate this application
with traditional method.
So, here first you need to create your
module by scanning, right? Click on
module scan.
And then, this is my web application.
Click on start scan.
This will open the launcher.
So, this opens you XScan. Okay? So, it's
as same as the Tricentis Tosca desktop
application. So, here I'm going to
select the
Tricentis vehicle insurance application.
Click on scan. So, by using this XScan,
we will be scanning all the elements
that are required to automate the
application. Right? So, let's quickly
scan them.
So, click on select on screen.
So, let's say I want to scan this
button.
And then finish screen because I've
completed my first screen. Right? So,
now once it is done,
then you need to enter your vehicle
data. So, let me again scan this vehicle
data.
So, here scan screen.
Now, we need to scan all the elements
related to vehicle data.
And then next button as well. Once you
finish scanning all your elements that
are required for the automation, you
just simply say finish scan and close
it.
So, what it will do, it will store all
the modules. Let's refresh this page,
okay? Let's go back to test cases.
And then let's come back again modules.
See here, these two are the modules that
we just now captured. Now, let's go to
test cases.
And let me create a new test case here,
okay? So, once we
complete creating modules, now it's time
for us to create the test case.
So, click on new test case. So, here I
don't want to create a new module
because I've already scanned the
modules. Go to user assets. So, these
are the modules I've already scanned,
right? So, let's use one of them, okay?
So, here let's use the modules that we
already scanned. So, here I'm going to
simply add this module as it is.
Perfect. And then, I would like to add
my vehicle data as well.
Add here.
So, now we need to enter the information
here. This is my get a quote button,
right? So, I'm going to click on this
button.
Now, you need to enter test data for the
vehicle data as well. So, you need to
perform all these activities manually.
So, here you need to enter everything.
So, here kilowatts. Let's say I want to
enter 1,000
1,000. And what is the
manufacturing date? It says 08
2024, right? And then you'll be
selecting number of seats. You need to
enter your list price, annual mileage,
and everything, right? So, basically you
need to enter all the information
manually. So, how many steps that are
involved? You need to first scan your
elements,
store the elements into your modules,
and then you need to create your test
cases by mapping the modules, and then
you need to enter the data for each
step, and then save the test case, and
then you need to execute the test case
to debug any issues. So, in the
traditional method, you need to perform
multiple steps.
What if you need not to scan any
elements?
You need not to create test cases. You
need not to enter your test steps. You
need not to enter the test data for test
steps.
What if you need not to perform all
these activities?
What if you can
create your modules, test steps, test
data, and you can run the test case with
simple natural language prompting?
What if you need not to perform all
these activities to automate the test
case?
You just pass the natural language, your
agentic AI will take care of creating
modules, your agentic AI will take care
of creating the test cases. You need not
to perform a single action that we
performed earlier.
You just pass the natural language
steps that you need to perform to your
agentic AI
test automation, and your agent will
take care of creating the modules, test
cases, and running the test cases, and
providing the test results. End-to-end
automation will be taken care by your
Tosca agentic test automation itself.
Now, let me show you how can we perform
end-to-end test automation
with simple natural language.
So, this is my Tricentis Tosca cloud
application
uh where I have registered by using the
organization address. Once you navigate
to Tricentis Tosca cloud application,
there are two important steps that you
need to follow.
So, to build a complex test combining
any technology that we currently
support, you need to be on Windows and
install some local components. What are
those? One is you need to install the
launcher.
So, this launcher is a small app that
gets everything that you needed to
automate your test cases. You need to
click on this download launcher.
This will download and install the
launcher. And then, you also need to
install the browser extension. To test
any web application, you need Tricentis
automation extension for the Chrome.
Right? So, this is mandatory. So, you'll
be installing this so that you can start
automating your web applications. So,
these two are needed. Once you complete
installing these two, so now let us see
what is the system under test web
application that we are considering to
automate the test cases with simple
natural language. So, this is our
motorcycle insurance application
developed by Tricentis. It is a sample
application for the insurance.
So, here once you land onto this
particular URL, I'm going to paste this
URL in the description. And then click
on get a quote to get automobile
insurance, you're going to click on get
a quote button. And then, you need to
select make of your vehicle.
Audi. And then, you need to select what
is the engine performance.
How many kilowatts? Let's enter some
kilowatts. And then you need to select
the date of manufacturing.
Right? And then, you need to select
number of seats
that are available in the vehicle.
And then what is the fuel type? Is it
diesel or petrol? Right? And then, what
is the price of your vehicle?
And once you enter the price of your
vehicle in the dollars, then you need to
enter your license plate number.
And then, what is your annual mileage
for your vehicle?
Once you enter all the required
information, we'll be clicking on next
button. And now, you're landing onto
enter insurance data. Once you land onto
the enter insurance data page, again you
need to fill all this information.
However, once you land onto this
particular page, I'm going to verify
that there is a first name and last name
fields are available. Okay? So, we are
going to stop at this point. Okay? So,
basically I need to automate
the application related to insurance
where I'll be entering the vehicle data.
And then, once I land onto the insurance
data, I'm going to validate that these
fields are available. Okay? So, now to
achieve this, I've already created a
natural language prompt.
So, this is my natural language prompt.
What is my application URL? This is my
application URL. What is my first step?
I need to click on get a quote button,
so this is the get quote button. Once I
click on get quote button,
and now select make drop down value as
Audi.
Right? Select the make drop down value
as Audi.
And then, enter engine performance.
And then, enter date of manufacture. And
then, select number of seats from drop
down. Select fuel type from from drop
down as diesel. And then, enter
payload.
And then, [clears throat] enter total
weight.
Enter list price. Enter license plate.
Enter annual mileage. Once you enter all
the details, then you'll be clicking on
next button. Right? And then, once I
click on next button, how can I make
sure that I have landed onto enter
insurance data page? By validating some
of the fields. I'm going to validate
first name and last name. What I
specified here? Check and validate that
first name field is visible.
Check and validate that last name field
is visible. So, this is my simple
natural language prompt file that
contains 15 different steps.
Okay? So, let's close this.
Now,
by using that natural language
prompting, we are going to automate the
test cases. So, before I start
automating the test cases by using
Agentic AI, let me show you what are all
the builds that are available. Let's go
to all assets in my
cloud instance. So, if you see here, in
this particular workspace, I don't have
any assets. I don't have modules.
I don't have reusable test steps. I
don't have test cases. Right? Everything
is empty. Now, let's see the magic of
your
Tosca Agentic test automation. See here,
this is your
icon, Tosca Agentic test automation
icon.
I'm not going to perform any scanning of
your elements. I'm not going to perform
any
test steps creation, test data creation,
etc. As we did in the traditional
method. And so, now let me open Tosca
Agentic test automation. So, before that
let me show you one more thing here.
Okay? If I go to agents, I've already
configured my local agent.
So, this is my local
desktop or this is my local laptop where
I'll be running the test from this cloud
application. Because this is your cloud
application. This is not my desktop
Tosca application. So, that is why you
need an agent to be established. This is
my local agent, personal local agent.
Okay? So, again, let's go back to our
home page.
And then here, let's click on Tosca
Agentic test automation.
As soon as you click on Tosca Agentic
test automation, this will initialize
your
window called Tosca Agentic test
automation. So, you can see here your
new favorite AI assistant is ready to
help.
Find, understand, optimize test assets
in simple natural language. Okay? So,
what I'm going to do here? I'm going to
generate the test case, right? Click on
generate a test case.
Now, till date, whenever you automate
your test cases by using natural
language or by using agents, in the past
we used to have only Vision AI, which
means once you create
test cases from natural language prompt,
all the modules that we are creating in
Tosca are related to Vision AI. We never
have the support for TBox.
So, now recently Tricentis Tosca
enhanced their Agentic test automation
for TBox modules as well. That means by
using simple natural language, now you
can create your test cases and you can
create your modules in TBox as well.
Basically, you can create TBox modules
as well. Not only Vision AI modules. In
the past in the past, we used to create
only Vision AI modules by using the
Agentic AI
automation.
So, now they expanded to create the TBox
modules as well. So, TBox modules are
very powerful compared to Vision AI
module for maintenance purpose. So, now
let me select TBox.
And now, click on continue. As soon as
you click on continue, it will ask you
to open the launcher.
So, in the past we already installed the
launcher, right? So, if you don't
install the launcher, then
it will not be able to open the
launcher. Click on open launcher.
So, here it says initializing TBox
inspection agent because I've selected
the TBox. If you select the Vision AI,
then it's going to initialize Vision AI
agent.
So, now it is establishing a connection.
And this will open the application
windows, how many application windows
that are available. If you see here,
I've already opened Edge
insurance application. Let me go to home
page
and keep this ready.
Okay? Let's go back to Tosca cloud.
Here, let me refresh the pages.
So, now it is asking us to select a
window
which you would like to automate. So,
this is my window, right? Because this
window contains my insurance
application. See? Tricentis vehicle
insurance application. Select this. Once
you select this application, now you can
see right side your application and the
left side you have agent prompt window.
So, this is your agent prompt window.
And you can see here you selected TBox
agent here.
So, now let me go back to my system.
So, this is the
AI natural language prompt that I have
showed you earlier, right? So, this is
the prompt I have entered in a file.
Basically, I have stored this into a
notepad. Okay?
There are two methods. Either you can
directly go and enter the instructions
in the chat box
so that it will start automating the
test case directly from the
natural language. Or
the another method is you can
attach the prompt. Attach the prompt
file. So, I'm going to attach the prompt
file here. So, this is my prompt file.
And here,
I would like to select
the mode here. If you select co-create
mode,
the agent will ask for your approval and
it gives you questions to answer, right?
For every step. But here, I would like
to go with the autonomous mode.
Autonomous mode means the agent will
take care everything based on the
natural language prompt that you
entered. Here, what I'm going to say?
Get a quote
for
insurance.
Get a quote for insurance. That's it.
And because
So, here I'm just entering one sentence,
get a quote for insurance because I have
entered all the natural language prompt
steps
in this particular file, right? And
then,
hit enter. As soon as you hit enter, it
will start reading line by line the
prompt file. And then, it will start
interacting with the web application.
See here, now it opened your insurance.
Now, it should click on get a quote
button.
See here, it clicked on button.
And now, what it will do, it will create
module, the Tosca module
for all these elements in the page. And
also, it will start interacting with
these fields by entering the values.
See here now, it started entering the
values. See how fast it is doing. And
then, it clicked on next button. Now
here, I asked Tosca to validate if user
lands onto enter insurance data and
validate first name, last name.
See now, I got a notification saying,
"Please go back to automation window."
Okay? Alt tab.
So, now here you can see
it performed all the operations. See
here, the test case is finished. Let's
save it. So, now I'm going to save the
test case. Save test case. Now, if you
see here in the past, we don't have this
option. So, you have now option either
you want to create a new module or do
you want to use the existing modules if
you have any modules in the past.
But, when I showed you in my workspace,
I don't have any modules. So, I'm going
to say keep new modules.
Perfect. Now, it is sending entire test
case data including the modules to your
Tricentis Tosca. See here, test case is
saved. Check out here. See here, it
already provided the link also.
Click on this link that will take you to
the new test case that is created.
So, here now. So, let's go to builder
again, okay? So, this is your test case.
So, let me go back to the builder so
that you will understand. Go to build
all assets.
See now, you see here now, go to
modules. So, if when I go to modules, I
can see these two modules are created.
Perfect. And let us go to test case.
See here, this is my test case.
Get insurance quote vehicle data. Open
this.
Now, see here,
I can see the test steps, everything
here. See, I can see the test steps and
everything.
Now, let's do one thing. Let us just run
the test case and see
whether it's going to work or not. I've
already selected a browser as
Edge. If you want to add any new
parameter, you can add new parameter
here, okay? I've already added a
parameter called browser with Edge,
okay? So, I have already opened this
Edge URL here, okay? Now, let us run the
test.
See here, it started running. Clicked on
get quote, and then perfect, it filled
everything. And now, it's validated. So,
let's go back here now. And now, let's
go to
view last run.
Click on view last run
and see if it is passed.
See here, your test steps are passed.
All the test steps are passed. See,
everything is status is showing as
passed. See how easy it is. I'm able to
create the entire test cases, right? And
also, I'm able to create the modules
also. See here, under modules, how many
uh
under modules, see, these are all the
elements that we already created.
See?
You have all these elements. I'm not
capturing all these by using
T-Box, by using scanner, right? So, I
did not use any scanning also. I just
used my simple
natural language prompt. I'm able to
create modules, and then I'm able to
create the test cases as well.
Right? So, how easy it is to create your
test cases and the modules by using
Tosca agent test automation. So, as I
told you, now your agentic AI test
automation supports the T-Box modules as
well. So, here you can see all the T-Box
modules. These are not my
Vision AI modules. See here, these are
all my T-Box modules. Because you see
here, each property shows you T-Box.
These are all T-Box properties. It's not
your Vision AI properties.
So, if you have any queries, leave your
queries in the comment box. I'll try to
respond to your queries.
So, in my next session, we're going to
start automating more complex test
cases, more complex end-to-end test
cases by using the natural language
prompting.
Hope you all understand the concepts of
today's lesson
where we were able to automate the
end-to-end test case
with simple natural language prompting
with the help of latest agentic AI
capabilities introduced by Tricentis
Tosca. So, your agent itself takes care
of creating the modules, element
locators, and then creating the test
cases and the test steps, and also
providing the test step values, and also
executing your test cases. All these
actions will be performed and taken care
by your agent itself. And as I told you,
Tricentis Tosca has enhanced agentic AI
capabilities for T-Box modules, also.
Please do subscribe to the channel.
Click on the bell icon. You'll receive
notifications whenever I publish more
videos. Don't forget to like and share
the video.
Thank you.